been thinking about mindfulness and um
well the difference between like
thinking that you need to constantly
like not even going into the
contemporary views of what mindfulness
is but even the the idea that you need
to be like constantly rehearsing ideas
and stuff and you know, however accurate
they are, you know, sutas and whatnot
versus just
the ability to sort of
I I was I was trying to think of a good
way to put it earlier, but kind of just
chuck something in the back, so to
speak, >> and know that it'll be there when it is
>> and know that it'll be there when it is
necessary. Mhm.
>> Um, namely, well, to give an example,
just, uh, like if you notice that there
are certain circumstances where you're
more likely to act out unh wholesomely.
>> Mhm.
>> You don't need to like be reminding
yourself of that throughout the day. Um,
>> why?
>> So, sorry.
>> Why? Well, like like you don't need to
be constantly going over it because
there's >> So, how would you prevent yourself from
>> So, how would you prevent yourself from
acting out if you're constantly
reminding yourself,
>> right? Well, you just That's kind of
where I wanted to bring up the
conversation is
>> like it's obvious that there are things
that you just remember when they're
relevant. >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> But
there are also things you don't remember
when it's relevant. So what's the
difference there if it's not just
constantly like keeping something tied in front of
like keeping something tied in front of
your face?
>> So but is it like that you just remember
random facts and they stay there like I
I can just um I don't know think about
the age of the universe and then keep
that at the back of my mind. Is that the
type of um context that we're talking
about or is there a reason why you're
able to keep certain things in mind?
>> Well, to answer your question, no.
>> It's not just random facts. It's more, I
guess, >> well, what that leads me to think of is
>> well, what that leads me to think of is
when you encounter something that you're
familiar with,
>> you'll have ideas about it, so to speak.
um whether those ideas are this is
something I should do, this is something
I shouldn't do, so to speak.
Um
>> but then
>> but that would be like okay you you
encounter things but that would be like
a very particular kind of let's say
particular events
>> and it's not like the mindfulness should
be there only at those times because
>> strictly speaking all the time you have
something happening
>> right
>> like so uh you might kind of bring up
the mindfulness in those specific
moments that will prevent you from kind
of acting out too much but you also want
to have mindfulness pretty much
constantly ly in a way because
constantly you have the possibility of
creative aversion and delusion and it
might be there to lesser extents than
you kind of anticipate but any extent
fundamentally you have to deal with it.
So, how could you make sure that you
don't allow room for those even lesser
forms of those kind of completely
proliferated acting out of greed and
stuff that that you still keep those
things in check without constantly
having to remind yourself
>> because again like remembering random
facts um everybody knows of course
that's not going to work. Um, and random
facts doesn't just have to be things
about the world. It can also be like um
information like kind of that that you
heard from someone. Those thing those
things can be useful to point you to
what to do. But fundamentally, those are
just kind of like if you just get
Alzheimer's, you get
>> So, this isn't quite answering your
question yet, but just spinning off a
little bit of what you said, but you
bring us there, but um
I guess what I what I sort of had in
mind was
as you're refining your idea of what is
an unh wholesome mental state
>> kind of get these ideas like yeah it's
obviously not about the like physical
look of what you're doing
>> um and you kind of get these I don't
know you can get more subtle
uh pictures of what it looks like when
your mind is in one of these states but
I guess I'm kind of falling into the
like taking that and saying Oh, that's
not that's different. That's not also
just an appearance when in it it sort of
is, >> right?
>> right?
>> It's just more of a
like almost the appearance of what you
take your mind to be
>> and you're kind of saying, okay, when
that's there, then it's bad.
>> Well, that's that's the point. Yeah. You
you want to you you're going to have
some preconceived notion.
>> Mhm. But you want to upgrade that
preconceived notion to correspond closer
and closer to the root of the unhols
mental state because everybody knows
like when they kind of find themselves
shouting to someone like they know
>> oh I'm angry
>> but that's if that's your metric for
what >> but but it's a factual metric you know
>> but but it's a factual metric you know
it's like okay clearly when this happens
there's a angry mind
>> but um obviously that's not going to be
enough to uproot
anger at its core
>> if that's where you notice and stop
>> and factually like many people of course
do you do emphasizing the wrong things
emphasizing focusing techniques and
stuff they would never actually go
beyond that that um conception of what
anger is. It's like only when I am
angrily talking to someone I'm angry. So
therefore, factually it might feel like
if I just speak in a certain way, I'm
not angry anymore. But no, it's like
there's this whole entire layer behind
your speech. It's like why are you
talking to this person? As we said many
times before, even if you're talking in
the most lovely kind of uh voice,
there's a mental state there that's
getting you to do that without which you
probably otherwise wouldn't be doing it.
You can be annoyed talking out of
talking to someone nicely out of that
annoyance. And that's the appearance of
that annoyance that is not anymore as
coarse as you're shouting at someone is
what you want to for you. Now that needs
to become the the notion of what an
angry mind is. And then eventually what
you're taking like what you're seeing
for that
could eventually just be another like
that could be need refinement further.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Eventually you get used to
that and then
>> but obviously now that all that
refinement would be mental like it would
just be more discerning further
indications like that simile of the of
the king like um initially maybe you
need to see him like make a certain
movement like when he he doesn't say it
>> he just makes a certain movement or
makes a certain facial expression when
he's seeing the food
>> but then you start to discern even more
peripheral things like I don't know um
things that are not more as um explicit
and that's that's a refinement of your
discernment of the sign of time. But the
point is whichever
to go back to the question of
mindfulness, whichever
uh level of refinement you have, why is
it that you can be mindful of things
such as that and a wholesome mental
state or a wholesome mental state
>> and not your friend random facts? What's
the difference?
cuz you know like I I if if you can
maintain a certain mindfulness of like
my mind is angry and you wouldn't be
able to to forget that unless you get
careless and get involved with that
angry mind.
>> You mean still like on the level of not
fully seeing the signs of the mind.
>> No, let's say you see it to some extent.
Let's say
>> like you have an idea and it's not just
like the course I'm yelling at somebody.
>> Whatever extent you have.
>> Yeah.
>> Let's say you see the mind is angry
right now. Why is it that you could stay
mindful of that but not like just
mindful of
>> what's going to happen tomorrow or
>> something?
>> Because it's like presently there like
it's you're not having to
>> create the fact that like something just
irrelevant to your experience like the
number of rings Saturn has or
>> that's that's the whole point. So that's
why the satipanas are
>> well they are
>> well that that's why they are the like
right mindfulness is defined as a
satanas >> not as just kind of remembering
>> not as just kind of remembering
>> anything in a certain way.
>> No it's remembering these specific
things. Now of course
>> uh when I say specific I don't mean like
you focus on them. Uh I mean it's the
these are things that inevitably
regardless of how far you go, regardless
of how you travel, what you're thinking
about, how special you are, these things
these are the four kind of cornerstones
of your experience. They have to be
there all the time.
>> Mh.
>> So in other words, you can develop
mindfulness of these things because they
are already there.
>> Like you're already conscious of them.
Consciousness is not awareness.
Consciousness is just the fact that the
thing is present. So
>> you don't need to generate it.
>> Exactly. So because of that
>> in order to keep yourself mindful
>> basically your awareness will be
occupied with wrong things.
So things that you're also conscious of.
You can't be aware of something without
being conscious of it. But you want to
then um make sure to that your awareness
applies to those relevant things rather
than just getting scattered into
concerns that are secondary that
actually take you away from those uh
foundations of your experience. So
when you're established in those, that's
when you can rightly say that only an
intentional choice of forgetting
will result in forgetting because you
are conscious of these things. It's like
even if you don't want them to be there,
they're there.
>> If it were something else like a random
fact, you would forget because it's just
a it's a it's a valitional
thing that you brought up. And then the
intention to think about it fades and
then it disappears.
>> Right? Like you can like very earnestly
think I'm going to do this
>> or very earnestly like when people have
um let's say uh something very important
for them to do.
>> Mhm.
>> And then they continuously kind of keep
in mind like oh I have to do this. I
have to do this.
>> Mhm.
>> Or or just trying to study. That's it.
That's that probably better example like
you you want to keep this stuff in mind
because you haven't examined or
whatever. >> But factually it just goes goes away.
>> But factually it just goes goes away.
>> Yeah.
>> Because you can cease to be conscious of
those things. It's like it's not a it's
not a concrete phenomenon that's there
all the time. But when it comes to these
four foundations,
whether you remember what you were
studying or not, your body will still be
there. You'll still feel a certain way.
you'll still be in a certain mood and um
you'll still have phenomena.
>> This is
this is where kind of adopting a
first person point of view is quite
important because you could say like oh
well you still factually have the test
>> even if you get Alzheimer's and like
factually you don't know about it.
>> Yeah.
>> Um that's very different than saying
factually you still have a body.
>> Yeah. Yeah. if you are taking on that
because like factually you don't know
that you have a test. Exactly. Yeah.
>> Yeah. So um that's why that's how then
mindfulness becomes effortless. It it
doesn't become something that you do.
It's like you like you said what what
was the comparison you said like you
throw something
>> just kind of toss it in the back.
>> Yeah.
>> But see it has to be something that's
already at the back.
>> I see
>> for that to work. Yeah. Yeah.
>> That's the whole point.
>> It can't just be
>> it can't just be a random thing. So,
it's not that even that you're tossing
it at the back. It's like you have to
see that it's already at the back.
Whether you toss it or not, that's the
only way that it's going to become
established. >> And then then from that perspective,
>> And then then from that perspective,
it's going to feel like if you fall away
from it, you're kind of
um descending down from a knowledge that
was already there. you're def you're
descending down into further activity
and proliferation. Whereas if it's the
other way around, if your mindfulness is
something that you're doing, then that's
now your your mindfulness is your
proliferation is your um engagement.
>> If um if those four phenomena
on um
if it's not possible to rightly discern
them in the sense of having right view.
>> Okay.
>> The thing is you have to be trying to
discern them.
>> Yeah.
>> That's how you get through.
>> I I wanted to ask what would be the
closest thing to write mindfulness then
to practice this kind. Well, uh, in a
way, first of all, yeah, keeping in mind
you haven't still understood them
>> or understood how to discern them for as
long as you don't have the right view.
That should be kind of before whatever
mindfulness you're trying to do.
>> But if you do it on the basis of that,
then it becomes a different whole
different thing because you're actually
trying to upgrade whatever you're doing.
You're not taking it for granted
anymore. So that's factually another
form of mindfulness that a person could
have. It's like no matter what
um novelty kind of developments occur in
their practice,
staying mindful of the fact that they're
still liable to suffering and that
liability is a factual thing as well.
You feel that threat of like if certain
things were to happen to me, my mind is
in such a place that it would suffer
quite a bit. And um in and of itself if
you that that recognition would be like
a form of let's say being mindful of um
oh doesn't even say like he knows uh a
mind that is not liberated as a mind
that is not liberated and factually that
would bring you closer to liberation
rather than then trying to fabricate
what you think liberation is
>> because liberation comes out of
precisely ignorance like not not
understanding these fundamental
phenomena. So if you were to develop
that clear awareness in the right sense
of a of a mind that's liable to
suffering, you would remove the
necessary basis or the fuel that was
causing that suffering. It might not
disappear right away, but when you're
aware of your liability to suffering,
you won't be doing certain things
anymore. You can just take it on that on that
You can just take it on that on that
very u general level like it's because
of ignoring the fact that I'm still
alive and suffering this problem is
still here that you become heapless and
just do things that undermine your own
goal.
How are you doing that? Why are you
doing like being mindful of I'm liable
to suffer
>> practically?
What like what what do you keep in mind?
What do you what do you tell yourself?
>> Well, let's let's try to explain that
then. How what would be the difference
between cuz it could easily just be an
abstract fact. I just sit down and I say
okay. >> That's just kind of like a again on the
>> That's just kind of like a again on the
same level as as like Saturn has x
amount of rings um
>> or repeating once just to keep your mind
occupied. >> But what is the concrete thing that you
>> But what is the concrete thing that you
could become established in? So that
that's not a just a thing that you tell
yourself anymore. M
>> it becomes an actual foundation of
mindfulness as the
>> phrase says
is that liability to suffering something
that you just reason
>> or it might be it's
>> it's not concrete in the sense of
>> Mhm. Mhm.
>> something that you can focus on.
>> So, it's got
I want to say
>> a sensation or something.
>> Yeah. Um,
>> but I mean it's it's present.
>> But what is it?
>> Just in terms
of description.
>> Well, I want to say it's like a
knowledge. just as a word like
>> you know that you're
>> but
>> liable to suffering.
>> Yeah. But
>> but there is something more
>> because that knowledge can also still be
abstract. >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. So what's the difference between
the knowledge that you now refer to and
just telling yourself I'm still liable
to suffering
>> because somebody could just get
convinced like in the same way that
they're convinced as a level of external
knowledge I am liable to suffering. They
could convince themselves I am not
liable to suffering
>> just based on like I that you get you're
given a list this is what it means to be
liable to suffering and you check all
the boxes okay that's it somebody gives
you a different list turns out you're
not liable to suffering
>> yeah that's why you cannot convince
someone to practice the dharmas they
have to
>> they have to see that they have to see
that liability but what is it
>> mhm
>> well isn't this same uh question is what
is suffering?
>> Yeah, in a way you can say
>> yeah.
>> So in relation to what do you most
acutely suffer?
>> Feeling.
>> There you go.
>> Oh yeah. On account of unpleasant
feelings.
>> But is it on like the liability itself?
Is it that it it's on account of
unpleasant feelings? In a way you could
say that but isn't the liability itself
a feeling as well
>> because I find
>> because that's the thing you don't want
to mystify like oh yeah the liability to
suffering is kind of
>> abstract identity. No no it's something
that you feel as well
>> because I find it's hard to think about
suffering when you're in a good mood
because you're just not
>> um like generally feeling bad.
>> Yeah. Yeah. But there is going to be
something that you can look at readily.
Yeah. >> The thing is it's there. Like you you're
>> The thing is it's there. Like you you're
not used to looking in that direction
>> because it
>> but you deep down know that if certain
things were to happen like it's it's
already there that that kind of
vulnerability or you could put it that
way. It's already there. you you it's
not like you kind of realize only once
the things happen because if if
something let's say something that you
that is dear to you were to um suddenly
be in danger and you find out it's not
like after it goes away after the thing
you lose it then you will realize oh I'm
suffering no it's like immediately when
you find out this might happen
you already know basically suffering is
already there.
>> Yeah. Which does mean that the more
comfortable somebody's life is and the
more they generally get what they want,
the harder it is to see this because
they now need to make a deliberate
effort in order to see that that their
good feelings and and and and their
moods depend on a host of things being
there taken for granted, but they're all
without exception impermanent. So if you
don't see that and you wait for that to
fall apart and only then do you realize
that you have a problem,
>> you have entirely overlooked the the
liability. So it's quite common for
people to be skeptical of the message of
the Buddha and the for saying what's all
this talk about suffering now all the
time most right but generally speaking
I'm doing quite okay
>> and then they begin to rationalize just
there yeah okay I I I understand 50
years from now I might be old I might
get sick but but I'll deal with it then
is a sort of common rationalization
>> failing to see that now all sorts of
things can happen and are happening that
you are already running away from you're
not even seeing that then
>> realistically you have to kind of um
bring it to the surface by thinking
about certain things and then it it
might even feel to you like okay I start
suffering only when I think about death
or only when I think about aging only
when I think about sickness from your
initial initial perspective might seem
that way but you realize the only reason
why these reflections were able to
trigger suffering is because you were
already in a state of suffering it's
just not as um course as you're used to.
It doesn't have these specific signs
that you expect an experience of
suffering to have which is like oh I'm
crying for many people I guess like or
or I'm about to start crying
>> um before then they might not even
realize that they're suffering.
>> So you're saying about anger.
>> Yeah, exactly. It's the same principle.
So you want to refine those recognitions
and see like even the liability to
suffering. The fact that nothing is
happening right now, but that anything
anything at all could happen and could
upset my mind to any extent. That's
suffering in itself because you're not
safe. It's like it's not something that
you can entirely forget about. Your
entire existence revolves around it. So
whatever you're doing, no matter how
small, is somehow related to the fact
that you're vulnerable to suffering.
>> Yeah. And so hope and fear is another
indication of this liability.
>> Mhm.
>> Because why why would you either fear or
hope, right? Hope and fear go together.
But why would you hope for or against
something? That's only because you know
that you are still liable to suffering.
>> But if you don't make that connection,
you can you can say hope is a good
thing. M
>> and then failing to see that as a sign
of more work to be done.
>> Yeah. It's it's you emphasize let's say
the positive aspect of oh yeah when this
thing that I want comes about
>> failing to see that you wanting that
thing >> is the first problem.
>> is the first problem.
>> Yeah.
>> Like whether you able to get it or not
>> that's now a separate thing.
>> Yeah.
So that means being mindful of your
viability to suffering is being mindful
of your feelings or being mindful of
your mind because it's it's factory
present in the same way that your u your
body is present.
Um but of course like because of the
whole perversion of the views people
would put all the emphasis on the body
and um like for myself I've rarely ever
heard anybody speak about how you're
mindful of your feelings or how you're
mindful of the mind unless they conflate
feelings with sensations to make it much
more palpable. But that whole dimension
of how you feel
without making making it kind of
objectified into it sensations is is
almost impossible for people to see or
it is impossible for people to see
unless they've developed themselves in
virtue like not acting out of certain
things which are already rooted in all
those feelings and mental states. So
when you don't act out of them, it's
like the dust settles, let's say, and
you're able to see, oh, this is what
would have led me to act out, and it
becomes clear. So that's why
even the sutras you you would see all
the time when people would come to to
ask the Buddha like for advice on
practicing mindfulness he would start by
saying you have to practice virtue which
when for you mindfulness is just
observation especially on the level of
sensations it would be almost seem like unconnected
it would be almost seem like unconnected
like why do I have to I could just start
watching my sensations right now but see
that's evidence of the fact that what
the Buddha is referring to as Body
is not what you think body is when you
can practice mindfulness of it without
virtue
cuz it's in that same direction. The
body that matters basically. It's that
direction that's underneath. The same
way your mental state is not something
that you can kind of pinpoint. Um the
the body that you're supposed to be
mindful of is on that same level. is the
body that undermines your ownership. Not
the body that you are relating to with
your ownership.
It's not even the body really. It's just
kind of yeah perceptions like it's not
even more any more special as I've said
before than just sounds
>> and smells than nobody tries to observe
their body by smelling things. Doesn't
make sense.
>> Yeah. The possibility of ownership is
also there only because of that more
fundamental body.
>> Yeah. Yeah. The possibility of uh
seeing, hearing, smelling, tasting,
touching, even thinking
>> is there because of that body that you
overlook and you descend onto the sense
objects. And uh if you that's why then if you
And uh if you that's why then if you
establish it you wouldn't need to keep
focusing on it because
>> sight sounds smells taste touches are
all secondary to it. That was the whole
point. So you don't need to keep making
your >> like returning to
>> like returning to
>> the perceptions of it as if those
perceptions are it.
>> Mhm.
And when you have recognized it to some
extent any of these things the body or
liability to suffering or um a hindrance
let's say
because that's also included. It doesn't
say that you kind of um
immediately when you do when you know a
hindrance the first thing you do is
replace it just think about something
else. It says that's part of the knowing
the hindrances, knowing how they arise,
how they cease and um so how would you
once you establish some context
prevent yourself from falling away from
without constantly bringing to life.
Realistically, you are going to fall
away from it. You figure it out like and
your ability to not lose track of it is
going to be probably proportionally
related to
how familiar you are with bringing
yourself back to the point where you
can't recognize it.
>> Sure. But um
>> yeah that that still doesn't answer the
question based on what you fall away
from. >> So so so how do you yeah what causes you
>> So so so how do you yeah what causes you
to fall away from it basically because
>> uh
it's is is it is is it your fault? Let's
start with that question.
>> Yes it is.
>> When you fall away from it is because
you didn't see yourself acting out of
it. >> Mhm. And it's just like this lack of
>> Mhm. And it's just like this lack of
recognition of just jumping into the
content >> but you basically act out and you didn't
>> but you basically act out and you didn't
see it basically.
>> So you fall away from it because you are
bit careless.
>> So So but so
how do you respond to that? Do you just
determine harder next time that I will
not distract myself?
>> No, you have to you have to recognize
like as somebody say like more clearer
where the line of your responsibility
is. It's kind of indirect, but in a way
it's very direct as well. It's kind of
>> Yeah, I'm saying that because naturally,
yes, you could recognize I fell away
from it because I chose to attend to
something else. But you also want to
recognize um it cannot be forced like you cannot
um it cannot be forced like you cannot
just as a matter of I decide now that I
will not fall away from the content
because that thing that is making you
fall away practically speaking is is so
close to you that you won't be able to
initially at least see it like okay
here's the option to uh distract myself
so I won't choose it quite the opposite
as as a result of persistence of
noticing yourself falling back and then
bringing it back again. That's how you
become less liable to falling away cuz
it's being reinforced like really the
reason why you fall away
even more accurately speaking is because
you still have an assumption.
You still have an assumption that allows
for you to believe that the body isn't
actually there when you go to think
about this or that.
That the feeling is not there anymore
when you kind of distract yourself with
entertainment or something that's going
to take you away from.
>> Can we say like maybe a bit maybe not a
bit abstract maybe, but can we say like
falling away is what you are?
>> Yeah. Yeah, that's right.
>> Well, actually that's why it says uh
based on assumption you have being.
If you don't fall away from the right
perspective, you could see at the very
least I may not be completely free from
being but that's the direction where
being will increase.
And there's that where I think it's
majima too where it says like um
understanding means understanding
means understanding
how your attention the things you attend
to lead to the increase of the influxes
of sensuality being and ignorance. I
think people read that line and it might
seem kind of abstract but it's factually
that like you you you see being as a
very kind of broad phenomenon. It's not
like you don't have like a a sensation
or an object of being. It's a whole kind
of
overall situation that comes to be on
account of you
emphasizing the content from in at the
expense of that foundation
background foundation that you have
recognized. So let's say you are
established in the knowledge that you
are right now liable to suffering. You
have a mind that's factually liable to
suffering not as an average idea but
something that a feeling there that you
have recognized
and then what's going to happen
is is it is it just going to stop there
if you don't undermine that liability
that liability will be what is hooked
that is what that's your assumptions
No, but let's say you saw it like you're
not no longer kind of
>> overlooking it. So let's say for now the
assumption is not there as strongly at
least as it was before.
>> So so that what happens next basically
>> that you ask if you need to do something
else. >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Like cuz
like is it going to stop there? Like you
just remember it and that's it. My mind
is established now.
You saw it. It's there factually.
But but what happens next?
>> Panic of having to keep it kind of what
you're seeing. I think
>> okay, that could be one option.
>> Yeah, that's fall away also.
>> That could be one option.
>> Or at least giving into the panic.
>> Or let's say doubt. Let's say even
before it becomes panic. Let's say you
have doubt.
>> I guess that's more what I mean more so.
>> Yeah. Like let's say um you're feeling
like okay, but is this really the
liability? like you you you saw it. It
it was a feeling of of um uncertainty,
vulnerability. It's like well maybe
maybe if I do something I can make this
liability go away quicker or something
or any any sort of direction that the
mind might try to
>> distract you with.
>> So the thing is that you want to discern
that you cannot establish your mind in
that perspective through action. Yeah,
you have to basically restrain yourself
from jumping into the content.
>> Yeah. So, so that's the thing like that
that's was that was what what I was
aiming at with the question. It's like
it will never feel like it's complete
because the mind will keep trying to
convince you that you need to do more.
You need to um increase the awareness or
something. And that's now the
bait that's pulling you back into the
content even if it feels completely
justified. And that's how you would fall
back into like you will increase your
being from where it's at now.
I know the the
ignorance as well will increase because
if you um
engage with that content that the mind
is trying to distract you with you will
find that it becomes harder and harder
to go back to that background that you
discerned initially. So that's why the
Buddha would say it's like um like a
what is it quo or something that should
um in regards to the sautan like it goes
into kind of like a hole.
>> Mhm.
>> And then the hawk comes and tries to get
it
>> but then it can't because
>> of course
>> like it's it's a hole. So
>> um and that's that's the that's the
whole point. It's not things for you to
kind of um just lose yourself in and
just forget about everything else. The
whole point is that things will be
coming up trying to take you away from
it. And uh you want to see you don't
want to be kind of fighting those things
by just no I won't think about these
things. I'll just think about the the
the the body or the feeling. It's like
they're not even on the same level. So
you cannot just replace one with the
other. Simply by staying with that
recognition at the background that
pretty much undermines all of these
things already,
they become irrelevant on their own
without you having to kind of push them
away cuz pushing them away would be
another way of you involving yourself
with them. If you saw that um basis of
your experience rightly, it wouldn't
occur to you to involve yourself with
these things cuz it's just like kind of
falling down from a higher place when
you were already safer than you were
when you engaged.
And then it's it's about sinking kind of
hammering in the fact that even though
it doesn't feel that way, even though
there is still the assumption that the
safety will come when I resolve the
content, when I have the answer that I'm
looking for,
>> no, the safety is when I stay here and
just even if these things come up, I see
through them. Like I I see them. I don't
just push them away. I don't just kind
of pretend that they that they don't
exist. I see them in relation to this
thing that I'm established in and I
prioritize that, not the things
That's why it means like you by
practicing satana you give up
covetousness and grief as often
translated in regard to the world. It
doesn't say oh he just forgets the
world. It will keep coming up. It has to. But
It will keep coming up. It has to. But
through this you purify yourself from
any tendency to just lean in that direction
tendency to just lean in that direction
carelessly again and just almost by
habit prioritize
anything like whether it's past,
present, future, here, there, other
people, yourself.
You don't have to deny any of those
things. They had to make sure that you
never put them first over
the the background, the foundation.
>> Yeah. Like now even just the word
foundation makes sense. But I remember
when I first started to practice like
meditation and stuff, they were talking
about like foundation of mindfulness and
stuff and it was like why don't you look
at your knee not like look at the tree
or something like why is that this one
is a foundation [Music]
>> yeah actually I think it's not an
exaggeration to say that people
basically ignore the other three
at best it's like a theoretical
explanation like oh when you're in your
meditation you examine the dharmas or
something that's it but not before that
you can't just see damas
>> yeah I mean unless the it kind of goes
into like you get to the point where
you're so advanced
>> watching the body that you can then
start to watch your mind
>> or feelings and
>> yeah whereas it's the other way around
that suta of simile of the cook says
unless you have grasp the sign of the
mind you will be doing this at the time
is wrong
>> so unless Unless you see your mind, you
can't somebody.
>> Yeah. Exactly.
>> Yeah.
>> Unless you are composing vent of the
right view, you cannot develop. It also
says that
>> I think there's something to say for the
fact that um
like to an extent some of these ideas
won't be
um practical for everybody. like
like it's not entirely obvious to me
that acting out is like a uh kind of
trying to step outside of the experience
as a whole. Um
>> well that's not how it's going to feel.
>> You would see it as such
>> cuz can you actually step outside of the
experience as a whole? Like if you were
aware of that even that idea you would
say like no this is not actually what
I'm doing.
>> Yeah. because it just seems like I'm
stepping somewhere else in my
experience. >> Yes. I mean, well, that's the assumption
>> Yes. I mean, well, that's the assumption
that you don't realize. If you were to
be aware of that assumption, you
wouldn't be able to have it because it's
ridiculous even in.
>> So it's it's uh
>> really you kind of start from the other
way around like you don't even see the
assumption >> and you might be told this is what
>> and you might be told this is what
you're assuming
>> and if you're just thinking in kind of
logical terms it's like no
>> no I'm not like
>> how would I be doing that?
>> Uh but it's it's factually what you
imply. Oh,
>> and then any anytime you bring yourself
back, you realize like, wait, this is
like how is how is I overlooking this?
Like it's completely obvious in a way.
>> But
>> but then you don't thinking about it.
You get there by doing it or by not
doing. >> Yeah. So that that's that's the
>> Yeah. So that that's that's the
important point like you will have to
think about let's when you lose it, you
will have to let's say attend to your
idea of what the body is. But if you've
received right instructions and you to
some extent have some sense of where to
look that idea should now become
secondary because you actually discern
the present
basis of the body that's independent of
whatever anybody whatever somebody told
you the body is and um that was the
other thing I was going to say once that
becomes established that's the whole
point of the um when the description of
satipana says uh Within the body he sees
the body. Within the feeling he sees the
feeling. Within the mind he sees the
mind. Within the within phenomena he
sees phenomena. It's you will have your
mind established
in a way effortlessly like independent
of your direct attention on one of these
things. And then you will naturally be
wanting to have thoughts about those
things. You want to be like clarifying
oh what is that feeling and is it did it
come from here did it come from there as
as says like um is it made by somebody
else is it made by me is it random is it
made by both uh what will I be tomorrow
what will it be tomorrow what will it be
later and
the whole point is within the presence
of that feeling that's there you see all
of this you see all of these ideas about
feelings things and then you then that's
how you will transcend any views that
you have in regard to it because you
will see wait this actually comes first
>> whether I say that it it's made by me or
it's made by somebody else
>> this this is what comes first
>> but if you let those ideas stand for the
feeling >> then you fall away from
>> then you fall away from
>> then you you start to then imply like
the feeling is the thing that will come
from clarifying these ideas
>> that's kind of the assumption that you
have to
>> the thing you're building with Legos
>> it's like I will arrive at the feeling
by clarifying these ideas.
>> Yeah, but that's that's where everyone
starts from.
>> Yeah,
>> that's what I said.
>> Yeah, you have to
>> but you have to first like when you
haven't seen it, you need to use these
ideas >> but you at the same time needs to be
>> but you at the same time needs to be
aware like okay these are just kind of
to point me towards where it is. But
when you're there you might still have
well very likely will still have the
tendency to think like oh the ideas will
help me. I need to keep keep going keep
going. But no, it's like right now if
you already established it now you need
to shift the order and see okay sure I
still have these ideas but I need to now
put this thing first that I have
recognized >> which doesn't mean that those ideas need
>> which doesn't mean that those ideas need
to disappear.
>> No no and actually that's how the ideas
would become more accurate.
>> Yeah
>> cuz then the they would be coming now
from the right order rather than just
>> kind of piling up information together.
>> Yeah.
Is that what's meant in some of the
sutas where it talks about um well for
instance like the bodhic sata thinking
oh well all of this thinking is tiring
for example
um or no I don't think it's that exa no
it's more the conceiving that the sutas
talk about
I think I'm
I forget exactly which sutas is it is a
talk about this but
>> 19 where he says like
>> he's been cultivating cult of
pronunciation >> right yeah where he kind of realizes
>> right yeah where he kind of realizes
like this isn't necessary anymore
>> yeah that's a slightly different
phenomena now this is in the context of
that there's something more refined than
even having thinking and wondering but
these conceivings not mistaking ideas of
body feeling mind and phenomena for
those establishment ments that have to
be there regardless of which ideas you
have. That's actually that's itself a
different dharma. Well, actually that's
that's what he
like in fact it says there he became
established in Janna when he said when
he realized these phenomena are there
explicitly says that people overlook
that completely and they think oh he
became established in Janna means like
he's he he he
became perfectly focused on one single
phenomena >> but no it says he after he was building
>> but no it says he after he was building
up these thoughts of renunciation and
planning his mind in that ction. He said
we realized this is not necessary
anymore. That doesn't mean he undid
those phenomena and went elsewhere. It
means he kind of uh established himself
in a more fundamental intention where he
his intention was just to see okay these
phenomena are there instead of just
trying to kind of keep doing them so to
speak. >> The renunciation the intention
>> The renunciation the intention
renunciation the the wholesome mind is
there. I have cultivated it already. I
don't need to keep building it. And
that's the that's when that's when he
shifted onto let's say proper
um satipana because in fact
um many of the sutas would say in order
to develop satipana you first start by
abandoning the five hindrances because
those are the ones that that are going
to be obstructing your clarity and
making you conceive even if you have the
perfect intention not to do so. conceive
the ideas about the body for the present
body that underrelies those ideas. So
once you've done away with the
hindrances which is what he was doing
like thinking when thoughts of
sensuality would arise he would think
about the danger and all that then he
was able to almost effortlessly have
this clarity like okay phenomena are
there
because satana in a way is already
the basis of samali
so say like it's the the nimas the
grounds of samati. So it's not like it's
two separate things like I cultivate
satana first and then samati comes. No,
being able to have perspective over the
body is already a level of somali that
you have might not be the first Janna,
but it's it's already that that aspect.
It's it's a unification like the mind is
unified in that background thing and and
isn't as much
kind of scattered among the content that
still arises.